Guide to the Hart Leadership Program records, 1995-2001 UA.22.02.0002
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Hart Leadership Program records
1995-2001
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Sanford School of Public Policy. Hart Leadership Program
UA.22.02.0002
1.0 Linear Feet
The Hart Leadership Program (HLP) is a part of the Sanford School of Public Policy at Duke University, offering courses and programs with a mission "to help students discover the power of leadership for public life." The Hart Leadership Program records include materials documenting the Service Opportunities in Leaderhship program and its predecessors, the Refugee Action Project and Interns in Conscience.
Biographical / Historical
The Hart Leadership Program (HLP) is a part of the Sanford School of Public Policy at Duke University. The HLP is a series of courses and programs with a mission "to help students discover the power of leadership for public life."
The Hart Leadership Program was founded in 1986 and is believed to be the first endowed leadership program for undergraduate students in the United States. Milledge A. Hart endowed the program, and Professor Bruce Payne was the founding director.
In addition to a variety of courses open to all undergraduate students at Duke, the HLP offers broader programs including Service Opportunities in Leadership (SOL), the Hart Fellowship Program (HFP), the Political Engagement Project, the Leadership and Arts Policy Internship, Research Service-Learning Pathways, and the Enterprising Leadership Initiative.
Service Opportunities in Leadership grew out of the Interns in Conscience program, a student-run program that facilitated student placement in summer internships with non-profit organizations from 1987-1992. In 1994, nine students worked on the Unaccompanied Children in Exile project in Croatia with then-HLP director Professor Neil Boothby; the following year the HLP created the Refugee Action Project (RAP) to place students in international summer internships. In 1996 HLP created Summer Opportunities in Leadership as a sister program placing students in the United States. In 1998, the two programs, RAP and SOL, merged into Service Opportunities in Leadership, and became a twelve-month program combining courses, mentoring, research, and leadership training.
Sources: Hart Leadership Program website, homepage, Purpose, and Program pages; https://hart.sanford.duke.edu/; accessed March 03 2021.
Access Restrictions
Access restricted. For a period of twenty-five years from the origin of the material, permission in writing from the office of origin and the University Archivist is required for use of administrative records. After twenty-five years, records that have been processed may be consulted with the permission of the University Archivist. Contact Research Services for more information.
Provenance
The Hart Leadership Program records were received by the Duke University Archives as a transfer in 2019.
Collection Overview
The Hart Leadership Program records include materials documenting the Service Opportunities in Leaderhship program and its predecessors, the Refugee Action Project and Interns in Conscience. The collection include correspondence, memorandums, reports, oral history interviews conducted by student participants in the program, and other materials.
Conditions Governing Access
Access note. Collection contains fragile audiovisual/photographic formats that may need to be reformatted before use. Contact Research Services for access.
Conditions Governing Access
Access restricted. Collection contains oral histories for which permissions may be needed. Contact Research Services for more information.
Leadership -- Study and teaching; Sanford School of Public Policy. Hart Leadership Program; Duke University--Students
- Accession UA2019.0068
  - From RAP to SOL (Box 1)
  - RAP Handouts (Box 1)
  - RAP Publicity/Funding (Box 1)
  - RAP Participants (Box 1)
  - RAP House Course, 1996 (Box 1)
  - RAP Placements, 1995-1996 (Box 1)
  - Suncokret: Croatia (Box 1)
  - RAP Change of plans, 1995 (Box 1)
  - RAP Vienna placement (Box 1)
  - Slovenia, 1995 (Box 1)
  - RAP Evaluations, 1995 (Box 1)
  - Report on summer 1995 RAP (Box 1)
  - Photos: Kathryn Andrews (Box 1)
  - RAP Follow-up, 1996 (Box 1)
  - SAGE (Students Against Genocide) (Box 1)
  - Rwanda: Lemkin (Box 1)
  - Addresses/Contacts: RAP, 1995 (Box 1)
  - Placements, 1996 (Box 1)
  - V.O.A. (Box 1)
  - RAP, 1997 (Box 1)
  - RAP slides, 1995 (Box 1)
  - House Course Papers: Samples, 1997 (Box 1)
  - Rwanda Duke (Box 1)
  - Interns in Conscience database list (Box 1)
  - GLASI (Global Leadership and Service Institute) (Box 1)
  - Correspondence from Maurice, Slovenia, 1995 (Box 1)
    Scope and Contents
    Includes information on cassette tape interviews; also includes 3.5" floppy disc titled "Claudia RAP info".
  - Interviews with Alma Isic, Valentina Lovisolo, 1995 June 28, 1995 June 30 (Box 1, Audio-cassette UA22020002-CS-0001)
  - Interviews with Rada Bjeljac, Hazim and Nusreta Pjanic, 1995 July 03, 1995 July 04 (Box 1, Audio-cassette UA22020002-CS-0002)
  - Interviews with Mirsada Lokvancic, Mike Banfield, 1995 (Box 1, Audio-cassette UA22020002-MCS-0001)
  - Interview with Husein Dzafic, 1995 (Box 1, Audio-cassette UA22020002-MCS-0002)